Guide to the Kenneth S. Wyatt Papers RG.023
Poly Archives & Special Collections at Bern Dibner Library of Science and Technology
Guide to the Kenneth S. Wyatt Papers, 1929-1967
RG.023
Poly Archives & Special Collections at Bern Dibner Library of Science and Technology
2.0 Cubic feet
Kenneth S. Wyatt (1900-1967) was a research engineer who worked to develop extra-high voltage cables, capable of insulating 500,000 volts. His papers contain articles, drafts, technical reports, conference proceedings, photographs, blueprints, and product samples.
Wyatt, Kenneth S., (Kenneth Sapwell), 1900-1967
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged into six series, by genre. Items within each series are arranged by subject, then chronologically.
Scope and Contents note
The collection, comprised mostly of articles and reports, spans Wyatt's active years in the electric cable industry. Companies such as Enfield Cable Works and Phelps Dodge are heavily represented. Although Wyatt's connection to Brooklyn Polytechnic Institute is noted through collaborative papers and presentations with professors Herman Mark and Frederick Eirich, there are no documents from Poly in the collection.
Besides articles, the collection contains photographs, product manuals and guides, conference proceedings, blueprints, and product samples.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research without restrictions.
Biographical/Historical note
Kenneth Sapwell Wyatt was born in Cambridge, Massachusetts in 1900. After two years of engineering studies at Mount Allison University in New Brunswick, Canada, he majored in physical chemistry and graduated in 1921 with a B.A. He earned a B.Sc. with honors in chemistry in 1922. After a year of graduate work at Harvard University, he became an assistant research chemist for the Carborundum Company in Niagara Falls, New York. He received a scholarship from the National Research Council of Canada and attended the University of Toronto in 1923. In 1961, Mount Allison University awarded him the degree of doctor of science, Honoris Causa.
Wyatt joined the research department of the Detroit Edison Company in 1928 and specialized in the study of the deterioration of high voltage insulation. During the 1930s, Wyatt was the technical director of Enfield Cable Works in London. In 1941, he became a consultant to the Phelps Dodge Copper Products Company of New York; a position that would last until his retirement in 1964.
Over the course of his career, Wyatt worked with polymer scientists, such as Brooklyn Polytechnic Institute's Herman Mark and Frederick Eirich, and electrical engineers to develop extra-high voltage cables, capable of insulating 500,000 volts. He was a member of the Edison metal committee of the Institute, the American Chemical Society (ACS), and the American Institute of Electrical Engineers (AIEE). In 1933, Wyatt and his co-authors W.E. Spring and C.H. Fellows, were awarded the A.I.E.E. national prize for initial paper for the contribution "A New Method of Investigating Cable Deterioration and Its Application to Service Aged Cable."
Wyatt died in Dobbs Ferry, NY on January 15, 1967.
Sources:
"Colleges Honor AIEE Fellows for Their Services in Engineering Field." Institute Activities. July 1961; 551.
"Personal Items." Electrical Engineering. Vol. 53, No. 7. July 1934; 1137.
"Kenneth S. Wyatt, at 66." Newsday, Nassau ed. 16 January 1967; 56.
Phelps Dodge Cable and Wire Company .; Polytechnic Institute of Brooklyn.; Articles; Chemical engineering; Electrical engineering; Patents; Photographs; Polymer engineering; Publications; Reprints
- Series I: Biographical Information, 1934-1967
  Scope and Contents note
  The biographical materials include industry publications noting Wyatt's achievements and Wyatt's obituary.
  - Biographical Information, 1934-1961 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series II: Correspondence, 1935-1963
  - Correspondence, 1935-1939 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1940, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1948 January - October (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1948 November - December (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1949 January - June (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1949 July - December (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1950 - 1956 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1960 - 1963 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Series III: Patents, Manuals, and Policies, 1931-1956
  - Patents, 1932-1952 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Habirshaw Cable and Wire Division Manuals, 1949-1951 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Les Cables De Lyon Manuals and Product Guides, 1950; undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bakelite Product Guide, 1948-1950; undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Manuals and Products guides, Miscellaneous, 1941-1949; undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Policies and Receipts, 1948-1956 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Series IV: Publications, 1929-1963
  - Subseries A: Articles, 1929-1963
    - Articles by Wyatt, 1938-1948 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Articles (many fragments) by Wyatt or Assumed to be by Wyatt, 1939-1952; undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Article Drafts by Wyatt, 1940-1948 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Articles not by Wyatt, 1929-1938 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Articles not by Wyatt, 1940-1949 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Articles not by Wyatt, 1950-1959 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Articles not by Wyatt, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Articles not by Wyatt, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Articles not by Wyatt (in French and German), 1930-1950 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Subseries B: Preprints and Reprints, 1929-1963
    - Preprints not by Wyatt, 1948-1963 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Reprints not by Wyatt, 1939-1962; undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Reprints not by Wyatt (in German), 1929-1957 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Reprints not by Wyatt (in French), 1940-1957; undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Subseries C: Reports, 1934-1962
    - Reports by Wyatt, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - C.R. Data- Costs, 1938-1940 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - C.R. - Special Reports, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Compression Cable Compensator Design, 1939-1949 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Enfield Rubber Sandwich Protection (contains product sample), 1934-1940 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Plastic Materials, 1937-1939 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Company Reports- Habirshaw Cable and Wire Division, Phelps Dodge Copper Products Corporation, 1940-1950 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Company Reports, 1937-1939 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Company Reports, 1946-1962 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Government Reports, 1941-1950; undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Technical Reports, 1938-1958 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Reports and Measurements, 1938-1950 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Subseries D: Journals, 1934-1963
    - The Electrician and The Electrical Times, 1938-1939 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Rural Engineering News, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Felton & Guilleaume Carlswerk Rundshau, 1934-1936 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous Journals, 1950-1963 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Subseries E: Conference Papers and Proceedings
    - Conference Reports by Wyatt, 1938-1961 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - C.I.G.R.E. Conference Papers, 1948-1962 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - American Petroleum Institute Proceedings, 1931-1934 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Institute of Electrical and Electronic Engineers Meeting Minutes, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Miscellaneous Conference Reports and Proceedings, 1937-1961 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Subseries F: Clippings, 1948-1961
    - Clippings, 1948-1961 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Series V: Graphic Materials, 1937-1951; undated
  - Kenneth Wyatt, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Elevator Supplies Company Inc., Rahway, NJ Photographs, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Elevator Supplies Company Inc., Rahway, NJ Photographs, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Blueprints, 1937-1951, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Maps, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Series VI: Miscellaneous, 1939-1963; undated
  - Notes, 1963 October 11, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Miscellaneous, 1939-1948; undated (Box 2, Folder 25)